Guide to the Houston Council of Texas Garden Clubs, Inc. Records
University of Houston Libraries
Houston Council of Texas Garden Clubs, Inc. Records
1943-2003
2003-002
Texas Garden Clubs. Houston Council
5.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The collection arrived in generally good order and condition. Some material from the late 1950s to early 1960s was very brittle, and has been placed in protective mylar. The collection includes an almost complete run of minutes, financials, and yearbooks.
Historical Note:
The Houston Council of Texas Garden Clubs, Inc. was organized and federated April 22, 1943. A number of Houston garden clubs united to establish a Council with the responsibility of coordinating the activities of local clubs at the state and national levels. A Constitution and By-Laws were adopted at the second Council meeting, in May 1943. After sixty years, the Council dissolved in June 2003 due to decreasing attendance of member clubs.
The Houston Council of Texas Garden Clubs was very active in the community throughout its existence. The Council’s two major community service projects regarded the United States Veterans Administration Hospital and the Lighthouse for the Blind Garden Club. These were ongoing projects over many years. The Council was involved in several activities at the hospital. Beginning in 1951, the Council provided weekly flower arrangements at the hospital chapel, maintained planter boxes, and created several gardens for use as garden therapy for the patients. The Council sponsored the Lighthouse for the Blind Garden Club, founded in 1949. The club provided transportation and activities for its members and Braille transcriptions of club rosters. The Council was also involved in smaller community service projects over the years.
For much of its existence, the Council met once a month, September through May, at the Houston Garden Center in Hermann Park. Officers were elected for two year terms, with elections held in May. Activities included instructional programs and presentations at the meetings, and annual flower shows.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Texas Garden Clubs. Houston Council
Genre/Form of Material:
Administrative records; Scrapbooks; Yearbooks
Topical Term:
Gardening; Women -- Societies and clubs -- Texas -- Houston
Acquisition Information:
Donation by the Houston Council of Texas Garden Clubs, Inc., 2003
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for Research.
Scope and Contents
The collection arrived in generally good order and condition. Some material from the late 1950s to early 1960s was very brittle, and has been placed in protective mylar. The collection includes an almost complete run of minutes, financials, and yearbooks.
The collection includes several large, typical scrapbooks and several smaller types of scrapbooks. These scrapbooks were compiled and submitted for various awards at the local and state levels. Most of the information on the Council’s two major activities, the Veterans Administration Hospital and the Lighthouse for the Blind Garden Club, as well as smaller projects, are contained in these books. The scrapbooks contain photographs, newspaper and magazine clippings, ribbons, correspondence, newsletters, and other material documenting the Council’s involvement in various community service projects.
The large scrapbooks were in very fragile condition. Items had been glued or taped onto the pages, most of the tape was no longer sticky, and items were loose throughout the books. The pages were very acidic and some had torn; some of the photographs had begun to discolor. Several of the scrapbooks contained loose material at the end. These scrapbooks have been disassembled for preservation purposes: pages with newsprint copied onto acid free paper, tape removed if possible, acid free tissue paper placed between the pages of the most fragile scrapbooks. The other type of scrapbook is a small, three-clasp pocket folder. These pocket folders have been disassembled and the material kept in original order.
The collection is divided into five series: Administrative, Projects and Activities, Awards, Yearbooks, and Memorabilia. The material in the collection has been arranged, for the most part, chronologically.
Detailed List of Contents
- Administrative
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material concerning the administration of the Council, including a history, correspondence, legal documents, newsletters, and an almost complete run of meeting minutes and financials. Financial information was included in the minutes until 1959. The minutes include those of the board of directors, the executive committee, and the general Council meetings, arranged chronologically. The minutes and financial material are arranged in two year increments corresponding to each president’s tenure.
  - History, 1943-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Legal Documents, 1958-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Minutes, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Minutes, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Minutes, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Minutes, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Minutes, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Minutes, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Minutes, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Minutes, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Minutes, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Minutes, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Minutes, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Minutes, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Minutes, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Minutes, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Minutes, 1999-2001 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Minutes, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Financials, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Financials, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Financials, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Financials, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Financials, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Financials, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Financials, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Financials, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Financials, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Financials, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Financials, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Financials, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Financials, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Financials, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Financials, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Financials, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Financials, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Financials, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Financials, 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Financials, 1999-2001 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Financials, 2001-2003 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Expenses, 2000-2003 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Dissolution Ballots, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 2001-2003 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Newsletters, 1963-1971 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Newsletters, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Newsletters, 1990-1993, 1996-1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Newsletters, 2000-2003 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Newsletter Production, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Projects and Activities
  This series contains material pertaining to the projects and activities of the Council, including community service projects and flower shows. It contains four sub-series: Community Service Projects, Flower Shows, Activities, and Related Organizations. Other projects are listed chronologically following the two main; the three other sub-series are also arranged chronologically. The Padre Island material contains original letters from Senator Lyndon Baines Johnson, Representative Albert Thomas, and Representative Bob Casey.
  - Community Service Projects
    - U.S. Veterans Administration Hospital, Garden Therapy Projects, (red scrapbook loose material and copies), 1952-1958 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - U.S. Veterans Administration Hospital, Garden Therapy Projects, (red scrapbook loose material and copies), 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - U.S. Veterans Administration Hospital Chapel, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - U.S. Veterans Administration Hospital Chapel, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - U.S. Veterans Administration Hospital Chapel, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - U.S. Veterans Administration Hospital Chapel, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - U.S. Veterans Administration Hospital Chapel, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Lighthouse for the Blind Garden Club, (white scrapbook loose material and copies), 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
    - Lighthouse for the Blind Garden Club, (black roses scrapbook loose material and copies), 1956-1963 (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
    - Lighthouse for the Blind Garden Club, (brown scrapbook loose material and copies), 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Lighthouse for the Blind Garden Club, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Lighthouse for the Blind Garden Club, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
    - Lighthouse for the Blind Garden Club, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
    - Blue Star Highway Memorial, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Lighthouse for the Blind Garden Club, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 35-36)
    - Fragrant Garden for the Blind, 1959-1969 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Padre Island National Park, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Padre Island National Park, Congressional Record, 86th Congress, vol. 105, no.159, September 9, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - High School Gardeners, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Huweiler Memorial Fountain, 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - U.S. Veterans Administration Hospital, Garden Therapy Projects, (red scrapbook), 1952-1960 (Box 5, Item 1)
    - Lighthouse for the Blind Garden Club, (white scrapbook), 1955-1961 (Box 5, Item 2)
    - Lighthouse for the Blind Garden Club, (black roses scrapbook), 1956-1963 (Box 5, Item 3)
    - Lighthouse for the Blind Garden Club, (brown scrapbook), 1963-1964 (Box 5, Item 4)
  - Flower Shows
    - First Houston International Flower and Garden Show, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Living with Flowers, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Song of the Sea, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Houston-International Gateway in the Spring, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Blossomtime Houston, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Showers of Flowers, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Fall Fantasy, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Springtime Jewels, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - A Prelude to Twenty, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - The Wonder of Christmas, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Magic, Myth, Mystery, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Carnival, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - A Time to…, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Honky Tonk USA, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Small and Beautiful, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Houston! NCS has Landed, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Cliches of the 90s, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Blossomtime Houston, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Wild and Free, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Flower Shows, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Activities
    - Meeting and Program, September 2001 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Meeting and Program, October 2001 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Meeting and Program, November 2001 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Meeting and Program, January 2002 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Meeting and Program, February 2002 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Meeting and Program, March 2002 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Meeting and Program, April 2002 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Meeting and Program, May 2002 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Meeting and Program, November 2002 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Meeting and Program, May 2003 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Meeting and Program, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Inner Circle, 1953-1957 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Houston Garden Center, 1955-2001 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Judges Council, 1956-1992 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Library, 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Miscellaneous Horticulture, 1963-2003 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Pilgrimages/Trips, 1985-1994 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Related Organizations
    - Garden Study Club of West University Place, (scrapbook loose material and copies), 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
    - District IV Coastal Prairie Council of Texas Garden Clubs, 1950s-2001 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Texas Garden Clubs, Inc., 1956-2003 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Houston Botanical Society, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Hunters Creek Garden Club Hunters Creek Heritage, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Arts and Flowers Garden Club Minutes, 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Arts and Flowers Garden Club Minutes, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Arts and Flowers Garden Club Minutes, 1995-1997 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Garden Study Club of West University Place, (scrapbook), 1940-1941 (Box 5, Item 5)
- Awards
  This series contains material pertaining to various awards received by the Council. It is divided into two sub-series: Community Service, and Gardening, both arranged chronologically.
  - Community Service
    - San Jacinto Girl Scouts, Inc., Certificate of Appreciation, March 12, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs, Garden Therapy, February 1965 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Veterans Administration Voluntary Service, April 15, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Lighthouse Community Service Award, May 12, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Houston American Revolution Bicentennial Commission, Particpation and Appreciation Awards, 1976 (Box 5, Item 6)
  - Gardening
    - Arbor Day, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Yearbook, 1963-1969 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Garden Club of the Year, 1963-1997 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Garden Council of the Year, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Flower Show Schedule, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Award Certificates, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Award Certificates, 1960s (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Award Certificates, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Award Certificates, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Award Certificates, 1990s (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Award Certificates, 2000s (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Award Certificates, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Yearbooks
  This series contains the Yearbooks of the Council, published every two years to coincide with the president’s tenure. 1973-1974 and 1989-1990 are missing.
  - 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - 2002-2003 (Box 4, Folder 48)
- Memorabilia
  This series contains miscellaneous items, such as the Council banner and seal, and four slides.
  - Four Slides, Fragrant Garden for the Blind, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Organization's Official Pocket Seal (Box 5, Item 7)
  - Organizational Banner, (OVS, outside of box) (Box 5, Item 8)